{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This thinker’s work The Sand Reckoner is the most comprehensive surviving source for Aristarchus’\nheliocentric theory. He was the first to develop formulas for the volume and surface area of a sphere and\ninvented a namesake “screw” used for raising water, but his “death ray” did not actually sink a fleet\nattacking his home, Syracuse. For ten points, name this scientist who supposedly ran through the streets\nshouting “Eureka!” after discovering the principle of buoyancy.",
      "answer": [
        "Archimedes of Syracuse",
        "Archimedes"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Prior to this event, the owner of Green Springs Plantation had tried to acquire warriors from the\nPamunkey queen Cockacoeske. Joseph Ingram failed to rally this movement after its leader died of\ndysentery. It grew from fear of Native American attacks and ended with the hangings of 23 rebels. For\nten points, name this 1676 rebellion against Virginia Governor William Berkeley in which Jamestown was\nburned to the ground.",
      "answer": [
        "Nathaniel Bacon’s Rebellion",
        "Bacon",
        "Bacon's Rebellion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this battle, an I-168 sank the USS Hammann, which was picking up survivors from a ship captained\nby Elliot Buckmaster; that ship lagged behind the Enterprise and Hornet. The USS Yorktown was lost,\nbut four Japanese carriers were destroyed in, for ten points, what decisive American victory, the turning\npoint of the Pacific theater of World War II?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Midway",
        "Midway"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This scientist beat Emile Berliner to the patent of the carbon transmitter and is attributed with\ncreating the world’s first industrial research and development lab, found in West Orange, New Jersey. The\nquote “genius is 1 percent inspiration and 99 percent perspiration” is attributed to this Wizard of Menlo\nPark. For ten points, name this prolific inventor of the phonograph, movie camera, and incandescent light\nbulb.",
      "answer": [
        "Thomas Edison",
        "Edison"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Michael Servetus believed that the soul could be found in this body system and was the first to\ncorrectly describe its function in the lungs. Marcello Malpighi confirmed a hypothesis about this system\nmade by a 17th century English physician about how two major components were connected. Robert\nJarvik developed a replacement for the major organ of this system, which was studied by Galen and\nWilliam Harvey. For ten points, name this body system consisting of the heart, blood, and blood vessels.",
      "answer": [
        "circulatory system",
        "cardiovascular system",
        "circulatory",
        "cardiovascular"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization controlled the Saarland for 15 years before a referendum supported German rule. It\ndid nothing in response to the Mukden incident, after which Japan withdrew from this organization. The\nU.S. Senate’s refusal to sign the Treaty of Versailles meant that the U.S. never joined this organization.\nFor ten points, name this international body that was unable to prevent World War II and was replaced\nby the United Nations.",
      "answer": "League of Nations"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer popularized a percussion-heavy style music inspired by Janissary bands with an opera\nin which Belmonte rescues Konstanze from Pasha Selim’s harem. He included heavy Masonic symbolism\nin an opera in which Tamino overcomes a series of trials with the help of the title woodwind. For ten\npoints, name this composer of The Abduction From The Seraglio and The Magic Flute.",
      "answer": [
        "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart",
        "Mozart"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these objects was taken by Vladimir Putin from Robert Kraft, who has earned four of them\nas an owner. The 1972 design symbolically includes 17 diamonds, and their designs often include gems\nand diamonds in the shapes of Roman numerals and the Vince Lombardi trophy. Tom Brady of the New\nEngland Patriots has four of, for ten points, what type of personal jewelry given to players and staff of\nteams who win the NFL championship?",
      "answer": "Super Bowl ring"
    },
    {
      "question": "One play depicting this event shows Giles Corey being executed with stones. Thomas Danforth and\nJohn Hathorne were heavily involved in this event, which was caused by the fits of Abigail Williams and\nBetty Parris, who were supposedly under the spell of slave Tituba. The Crucible depicted, for ten points,\nwhat 1690s event in which a Massachusetts town executed people for supposedly practicing magic?",
      "answer": "Salem Witch Trials"
    },
    {
      "question": "This family’s crest pictures a red cow eating grass against a yellow background. One member of this\nfamily hosted an orgy in the Banquet of the Chestnuts. That man, the enemy of Girolamo Savonarola,\nhad formed the League of Venice to oppose Charles VIII’s invasion of Italy. That man’s son had embarked\non the Romagna campaign, and was the inspiration for Niccolo Machiavelli’s The Prince. For ten points,\nname this Italian family whose members included Cesare and Pope Alexander VI.",
      "answer": [
        "Borgia family",
        "Borgia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What island off the coast of Italy is home to Cosa Nostra, a notorious crime syndicate\noften called “the Mafia?”",
      "answer": "Sicily"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A 1948 expiration date was set for a mandate for this region and a corresponding memorandum\nregarding Transjordan established by the League of Nations. Since the 1993 Oslo Accords, parts of this\nregion have been governed by a namesake National Authority currently led by Mahmoud Abbas. For ten\npoints, name this Middle Eastern region, home to a state that competes over claims on the West Bank\nand Gaza Strip, as well as a potential “two-state” solution, with Israel.",
        "answer": "Palestine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The State of Palestine was declared by this organization, considered a terrorist group by the\nU.S. until 1991.",
        "answer": [
          "Palestinian Liberation Organization",
          "PLO"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The neighborhood of Marble Hill was separated from this island by the construction of a canal in\n1895. Its original source of fresh water, Collect Pond, was landfilled and became the site of the Five Points\nslum. This island’s neighborhood of Battery Park City was built from land excavated from a Minoru\nYamasaki-designed skyscraper project, and a low-lying area in the north of this island became a center\nof African-American culture. For ten points, what island in New York City is home to Harlem and the\nWorld Trade Center?",
        "answer": "Manhattan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Battery Park City was built on the banks of what river, which separates Manhattan from New\nJersey?",
        "answer": [
          "Hudson River",
          "Hudson"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The patronage of Gushi Khan increased the power of the holders of this position. A delegate of one\nholder of this position was forced at gunpoint to ratify the Seventeen Point Agreement. Men who hold this\nposition are thought to be incarnations of Avalokiteshvara. The current holder of this position, Tenzin\nGyatso, currently lives in exile in India. For ten points, name this position, the spiritual leader of Tibetan\nBuddhism.",
        "answer": "Dalai Lama"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other form of Buddhism, which uses koans to teach Buddhist principles, is commonly\npracticed in Japan.",
        "answer": [
          "Zen Buddhism",
          "Zen"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This position was ended by the Peace of Pressburg, which also created the Confederation of the\nRhine. One holder of this position stood in the snow outside Canossa to do penance, and the successor to\nthis position was decided by the prince-electors. These men were crowned by popes until 1530, and the\nphrase “sacrum” was added to this title by a man who fought the Lombard League. For ten points, name\nthis position, which was held by Charles V and Frederick Barbarossa.",
        "answer": [
          "Holy Roman Emperor",
          "Romisch-deutscher Kaiser",
          "Romanorum Imperator"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A 1356 decree known by this color was issued by Charles IV to set the number of electors to\nselect the Holy Roman Emperor at seven.",
        "answer": [
          "Golden Bull of 1356",
          "Gold",
          "Bulla Aurea"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At least two governors of this state have publicly refused to return a Virginian Confederate flag won\nat the Battle of Gettysburg. One endured a state government shutdown in 2011; another was former professional wrestler Jesse Ventura. For ten points, name this state where Tim Walz\nof the Democratic-Farmer-Labor Party governs from St. Paul.",
        "answer": "Minnesota"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2007, 13 people died when this disaster struck Interstate 35 in Minneapolis, leading to calls\nfor increased funding for infrastructure.",
        "answer": [
          "a bridge collapsed into the Mississippi River",
          "bridge collapse"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This company’s John Archbold was almost assassinated in 1915 at Cedar Cliffs by members of the\nIWW. One of this company’s founders, Henry Flagler, is the namesake of the Florida east coast Railway.\nMuckraker Ida Tarbell wrote a history of this company, which was dissolved after it was found to be\nviolating the Sherman Antitrust Act in 1911. For ten points, name this petroleum company that was\ncreated by John D. Rockefeller.",
        "answer": [
          "Standard Oil Company",
          "Standard Oil"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Standard Oil is an example of this economic scenario which occurs when a single company or\nenterprise is the only provider of a commodity or service.",
        "answer": "monopoly"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man documents his experiences traveling in China in his collection “In Time of War: A Sonnet\nSequence with a Verse Commentary.” One poem by this author asks “Who can reach the deaf?/Who can\nspeak for the dumb?” and begins in “one of the dives/On Fifty-Second Street”; that poem declares “We\nmust love each other or die.” “Funeral Blues” was written by, for ten points, what poet who memorialized\nthe beginning of WWII in his poem “September 1, 1939?\"",
        "answer": [
          "W H Auden",
          "Auden",
          "Wystan Hugh Auden"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "”September 1, 1939” states that this ancient Greek historian knew “All that a speech can say\nabout/About Democracy,” alluding to his record of Pericles’ funeral oration in his most famous work.",
        "answer": "Thucydides"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Senussi opposed French influence on this continent in the early 20th century. The Battle of\nGazala was fought near a northern port on this continent, Tobruk, during the Western Desert Campaign;\nthat campaign culminated in the Second Battle of El Alamein, where Erwin Rommel’s forces were forced\nto retreat to this continent’s northernmost country, Tunisia. For ten points, name this continent where an\nAllied World War 2 campaign pushed the Germans out of Libyan and Egyptian deserts.",
        "answer": "Africa"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Erwin Rommel was known as the “Desert” one of these crafty animals.",
        "answer": [
          "Desert Fox",
          "Fox"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "NORTH AFRICAN CITIES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The capital of Libya, where Muammar Gaddafi ruled until 2011?",
          "answer": "Tripoli"
        },
        {
          "question": "The largest city in Morocco and setting of a classic 1943 film?",
          "answer": "Casablanca"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of a U.S. Embassy in Libya that was attacked on September 11, 2012?",
          "answer": "Benghazi"
        },
        {
          "question": "The former Phoenician colony whose earth was supposedly salted in 146 BCE?",
          "answer": "Carthage"
        },
        {
          "question": "The city in central Mali home to the Sankore Madrassa, popularly believed to be hard to reach?",
          "answer": "Timbuktu"
        },
        {
          "question": "The home of the Great Library, a Wonder of the Ancient World?",
          "answer": "Alexandria"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of a 1956 general strike and bombings of a milk bar and other French civilian targets by the\nFLN?",
          "answer": "Algiers"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of an Egyptian battle that Winston Churchill called “perhaps the end of the beginning?”",
          "answer": "El Alamein"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Which North African city is or was..."
    },
    {
      "category": "SPANISH-AMERICAN WAR",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The Caribbean island, with capital Havana, that gained independence from Spain after the war?",
          "answer": "Cuba"
        },
        {
          "question": "The U.S. battleship sunk in Havana harbor, triggering the war?",
          "answer": [
            "USS Maine",
            "Maine"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The future U.S. President who was second-in-command of the Rough Riders?",
          "answer": [
            "Theodore Roosevelt",
            "T Roosevelt"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The treaty that ended the war?",
          "answer": [
            "Treaty of Paris",
            "Paris"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The July 1st battle in which the Rough Riders and Buffalo Soldiers took Kettle Hill?",
          "answer": [
            "San Juan Hill",
            "San Juan Heights"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The Admiral of the Navy who won the Battle of Manila Bay?",
          "answer": [
            "George Dewey",
            "Dewey"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The Asian archipelago where Emilio Aguinaldo fought with, then against, the U.S.?",
          "answer": "Philippines"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Army Chief of Staff and surgeon whose brigade included the Rough Riders?",
          "answer": [
            "Leonard Wood",
            "Wood"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "During the Spanish-American War, who or what was..."
    },
    {
      "category": "MODERN BRITISH PMS",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is the current PM (2025)?",
          "answer": "Keir Starmer"
        },
        {
          "question": "served during most of World War II, offering nothing but “blood, toil, tears, and sweat?”",
          "answer": [
            "Winston Churchill",
            "Churchill"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "was known as the Iron Lady?",
          "answer": [
            "Margaret Thatcher",
            "Thatcher"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "attended the 1919 Paris Peace Conference and helped organize the Treaty of Versailles?",
          "answer": [
            "David Lloyd George",
            "Lloyd George"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "signed the Munich Agreement with Hitler, proclaiming “peace in our time”?",
          "answer": [
            "Neville Chamberlain",
            "Chamberlain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "replaced his predecessor as the new Labour PM at the 1945 Potsdam Conference?",
          "answer": [
            "Clement Attlee",
            "Attlee"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "was criticized for sending troops to Iraq in 2003?",
          "answer": [
            "Tony Blair",
            "Blair"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "was comparably less criticized for sending troops to Iraq in 1991?",
          "answer": [
            "John Major",
            "Major"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Which British Prime Minister from the 20th and 21st centuries..."
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One man involved in this event used the name John Johnson, and people involved in\nthis event took shelter at the Holbeche House. Francis (20 pts) ",
        "Tresham and Thomas Wintour\nwere executed for their role in this event, and the plan for this event was uncovered in an\nanonymous letter sent to Lord (10 pts) ",
        "Monteagle. Robert Catesby served as the leader behind this\nevent, which saw Guy Fawkes discovered guarding ammunition. For ten points, name this plot to blow up\nthe British Parliament and assassinate James I."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Gunpowder Plot",
        "Gunpowder",
        "Treason"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A radiator of this color can be seen in the lower left Edward Hopper’s Automat, and a\nflag of this color flies atop of the mast of Bosch’s Ship of Fools. Gauguin painted a symbolic (20 pts) ",
        "Christ of this color, which joins black, red, and blue as the only colors in most (10 pts) ",
        "Piet Mondrian [PEET MOHN-dree-AHN] works. For ten points, name this primary color featured in Van\nGogh’s Sunflowers."
      ],
      "answer": "yellow"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man took riverboats from Cairo, Illinois across the Mississippi river in his first\nbattle as commanding officer, the Battle of Belmont. He caused Nathan (20 pts) ",
        "Bedford\nForrest to flee Fort Donelson, where he demanded Simon Buckner’s immediate surrender.\nHis troops defended the (10 pts) ",
        "Hornet’s Nest at a battle where Albert Sidney Johnston was killed. For\nten points, name this victorious general at the Battle of Shiloh who earned the nickname “Unconditional\nSurrender,” partially for his initials."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ulysses S. Grant",
        "Grant"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) TANAPA manages this mountain’s Lemosho trail. First summited by Hans Meyer, it\nconsists three connected cones: Shira, Mawenzi, and one renamed by (20 pts) ",
        "Julius Nyerere\nto celebrate his nation’s independence, Kibo. This mountain’s Arrow Glacier doesn’t exist\nanymore, and all the ice on (10 pts) ",
        "its Uhuru Peak is expected to disappear by 2060. For ten points,\nwhat dormant, snow-capped volcano in Tanzania is the highest point in Africa?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mount Kilimanjaro",
        "Kilimanjaro"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to William of Poitiers, Pope Alexander II gave a papal banner to one leader\nprior to this battle. That leader led an attacking force landed in Pevensey, even though they\nintended to land in the (20 pts) ",
        "Isle of Wight. The other side in this battle had a defensive\nposition on Senlac Hill, where one losing leader was shot in the (10 pts) ",
        "eye. This battle is depicted\non the Bayeux Tapestry, which shows the death of Harold Godwinson. For ten points, name this 1066\nvictory for William the Conqueror, who afterward would establish Norman rule of England."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Hastings",
        "Hastings"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This god turned Caenis into a man so that she could become a warrior, and this god\nwas angered when (20 pts) ",
        "Laomedon refused to pay him for building the walls of Troy. This\ngod was defeated by (10 pts) ",
        "Athena in a contest for the patronage of Athens when her gift of the olive\ntree was judged superior to his gift of a saltwater spring. For ten points, name this Greek trident-wielding\ngod of the sea."
      ],
      "answer": "Poseidon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of this man’s first acts as Prime Minister was the First Agrarian Reform, which\nexpropriated large sugar plantations for redistributions to peasants. Before coming to power,\nhe was denied counsel in a trial over a failed (20 pts) ",
        "July 26th attack on the barracks at\nMoncada; at that trial, this man proclaimed “Condemn me; it does not matter. History will (10 pts) ",
        "absolve me.” After overthrowing Fulgencio Batista, this man ruled for half a century until passing\npower to his brother Raul in 2008. For ten points, name this longtime dictator of Cuba."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Fidel Castro",
        "Castro"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Ben Shahn created a painting depicting these people in coffins titled for their Passion.\nMario Buda probably assisted in the Wall Street (20 pts) ",
        "bombing two days after the indictment\nof these men, who were defended by Fred Moore for the (10 pts) ",
        "murder of Alessandro Berardelli\nduring a Massachusetts robbery in 1920. For ten points, name these two Italian anarchists whose death\nsentences were criticized worldwide as being politically motivated."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nicola Sacco and Bartolomeo Vanzetti",
        "Sacco and Vanzetti"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) In response to this event, Mossad launched Operation Wraith of God and\nOperation Spring of Youth. This event’s perpetrators demanded the release of\nAndreas Baader and (20 pts) ",
        "Ulrike Meinhoff, the founders of the Red Army Faction, (10 pts) ",
        "Haganah. For ten points, name this event that saw members of Black September kill 11 Israeli\ncoaches and athletes at the 1972 Summer Olympics in a certain German city."
      ],
      "answer": "Munich Massacre"
    }
  ]
}